this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
openzity is the only open source way to
embed zero trust networking into your
app giving you unprecedented control and
security
give your app superpowers using an
opencd sdk and a few lines of code
never face the horrors of vpns dns or
inbound ports
no networking engineering skills needed
openzd is trusted by developers at
microsoft oracle and ramco
if you don't want to host opencd
netfoundry can with free plans at
netfoundry.io
se radio that's n-e-t-f-o-u-n-d-r-y
dot io
s-e-radio
[Music]
hello and welcome to software
engineering radio my name is nikhil and
i am going to be your host today
and today we are going to be talking to
omar katz
omer is a software consultant based in
tel aviv israel a passionate open source
enthusiast umer has been programming for
over a decade and is a contributor to
multiple open source software projects
like celery engine and oplab omer
currently is also a
committer to the salary project and is
one of the administrators of the project
and he is the founder and ceo of the
caps consulting group he supports
high-tech enterprises and startups in
israel by providing solutions to
software architecture problems and
technical data welcome to the show man
and do you think uh i have covered your
extensive resume or do you feel that you
need to add something to it well
i'm married to a beautiful wife maya and
i have a son a two-year-old son itamar
which i'm very very proud of
and
it's very very hard to work on open
source projects
when you have these conditions with the
pandemic and you know life
cool
thanks so to the topic of discussion
today we're going to be talking about
distributed task queues and how celery
which is a python
implementation of a distributed task
queue
is set up right so we're going to do a
deep dive into how salary works
just so that our audience understands
why can you tell us what is a
distributed task queue and for what use
cases would one use a distributed task
view right so a task queue would be a
fiction in my opinion a task queue is
cert is just a worker that consumes
messages and executes code in
consequence it's a really weird concept
to you know use it as a type of software
instead of as a type of architectural
building block because
okay
cool so
how so you said you mentioned it is an
architectural building block
is the task queue just another name for
a job queue is a task no
naturally no
you can use a task queue
to execute jobs but you can use a
message queue
to publish messages that aren't
necessarily job they could be just data
or logs
that are not actionable by themselves
okay
so from a simple perspective so as a
software engineer
can i think of a task queue sort of like
a
engine or a means to do
execute tasks that are not
synchronous so can i make it something
about asynchronous execution of tasks
yeah i guess that's
that's the right uh
description of the architecture
component
but it's not really a queue of tasks
it's not a single key of tasks i think
the term does not really reflect
what salary or other
workers do
because the complexity behind it is
not just a single key you have a one
task queue
when you are a startup with two people
but the right term would be a task
processing framework because
salary can process tasks from one queue
multiple queues it can utilize the
broker topologies the broker allows for
example rabbitmq allows fanout so you
can send the same task to different
workers and each worker would do
something completely different
as long as the function name as the
task's name is the same you can create
topic exchanges which also work in redis
so you can route a task
to a specific cluster of
workers
which handle it differently than another
cluster just by the routing key routing
key is essentially a string
that
contains namespaces in it
and
a topic exchange
can provide a routing key as a glob
so you could exclude or include
certain patterns
right
okay so let's
dig into that a little bit so just to
contrast this a little bit more so there
is in when you talk about messaging
there are other models also in messaging
right so for example the actor model and
actors that are running in model can you
tell us what would be the difference
between
the architectural pattern of an actor
model and the one that we are talking
about today uh which is the task queue
yes well
the actual model has axioms
where task execution platform or engine
doesn't have any accents you can
run whatever you want with it one task
can do many things or one thing an actor
maintains the single responsibility
principle it only does one thing and
they communicate with each other what
salary allows is to execute
arbitrary code
that you've written in python
asynchronously using using a message
broker there are no real
constraints or
requirements to what you you can or can
do which is a problem because people try
to run their machine learning pipelines
with celery when there are far better
better tools for the class
okay
cool so as we say that a task you so
given this can you talk about some of
the
advantages or why would you actually
want to use
something like salary or a distributed
task queue or say a simple job manager
or a cron job of some sort well
salary is very very simple to set up
which
will always be the case because
i think we need a tool that can grow
from the startup stage to the enterprise
stage at this point
salary is for the startup stage
and
the growing company stage because
after that
things start to fail or cause unexpected
bugs because the conditions that the
the seller is in
is something that it was not designed
for when the project started i mean you
have to remember we haven't dealt with
this scale
back in the day even not in 2010 right
right and yeah so so one of the things
about salary that i've noticed is that
it is like you pointed out very easy to
set up uh and it is also
not a single library right so it uses a
messaging protocol or a message broker
to kind of run the actual queue itself
and the messaging itself so celery was
built on top of this other library
called kombu
and as i understand it combo is also
a message it's a wrapper around a
messaging protocol called amqp
right so can we step back a little bit
and talk about amqp what is amqp and why
is it a good fit for something like what
celery does okay nqp is the advanced
message queueing protocol but it has two
different protocols under that name
0.9.1
which
is the product called rabbitmq
implements
and 1.0
which is the protocol that not many
message brokers implement but apache
activemq does
which we don't support so it does not
support it yet also qp proton supports
it but we don't support that yet
so basically we have
a concept where there is a protocol that
defines
how we communicate
with our cues how do we route tasks to
cues what happens when they are consumed
now that protocol is not well defined
and it is apparent because rabbit and q
has an addendum as an errata
for it so things have changed and what
you read in the protocol isn't the
reference implementation because
rabbitmq is
the ones that were not known when
0.9.1 was conceived which for example is
the replication of cues
now rabbit mq introduced quorum cues
very very recently in previous days you
could not
keep a high highly available rabbit in
key instance easily
right
can we go a little bit more simpler
about okay
so
why is salary using a messaging protocol
as opposed to
you know like a you could just have some
entries in a database or a discount from
y messaging protocol right
so
amkp guarantees delivery at least once
delivered and that is a very very
interesting property for anyone who
wants to run something asynchronously
because
otherwise you'd have to take care of it
yourself tcp does not
guarantee an acknowledgement at the
application level so the most
fundamental thing about nqp is that it
was one of the
protocols that allowed you
to report on the state of the message it
is acknowledged because it's done it's
not acknowledged so we turn it to the
queue
it can also be rejected
and rejected and redelivered or not
and that that is a useful concept
because
let's say for example salary wants to
reject a message whenever the message
fails that is helpful because you can
then route the message to where messages
go when they fail so let's talk a bit
about exchanges in
amqp
0.9.1
and i'll explain that concept further
and why that's useful so exchanges are
basically where tasks land and decide
where to go you have a direct exchange
which just delivers the task to the
queue
it is bound on you can create bindings
between exchanges and queues
and if you bind a queue to the direct
exchange and the message is received in
that exchange the key will get it you
can have a fanout queue
which you find out exchange
which is how you deliver one message to
multiple queues
now
why is this useful in general
let's imagine you have a social network
with feeds so you want everyone who is
following someone to know that a new
post was created so you can reveal their
feed in the cache
so you can fan out at that post to all
the followers of that user from a fanout
exchange that was created just for that
user and then after you're done just
delete all of the topology
that will cause the message to be
consumed from each and every queue and
it would be inserted to each and every
user's feed cache for example right
right so that's a great point because
that kind of allows
one to see that salary which is built on
top of this messaging library can also
be configured to support these types of
scenarios right so you have a fan out
scenario or you have a pub sub scenario
or you have a direct queue consumption
scenario so it's not just that you have
to have one salary so can we talk about
a little bit about the celery library
itself because one thing i have noticed
about it is that it has got a plug-in
architecture right so the salary library
itself has got plugins for
the salary beat which is a scheduling
option and then
it has combo
it has also got you can also support
multiple different types of backend so
so maybe we can just step back a little
bit and talk about the basic components
that somebody would have to do install
or set up in order to implement salary
well if you implement salary you need a
framework that
maintains its different services
logically and that's what we have in
celery we have i had adopt framework for
running different processes in the same
process
so for example sara has its own event
loop that was written to make the
communication with the broker
asynchronous
and that is a component
and salary has a consumer which is also
a component
it has gossip mingle etc etc all of
these are pluggable now we control the
starting of stop and stopping of
components using boot steps
so you decide
which steps you want to run in order
and these steps require other steps so
you get you basically get an
initialization dag
okay
so we have the application which would
be our own application we kind of import
salary into it and then we have this
message broker is does this message this
message broker have to be
a rabbit mq or is there uh what are the
other types of message
back-ends that salary can support we
have many we have redis we have sqs
and we have many more which are not very
well maintained so there they're still
in experimental state and everybody is
welcome to contribute
right absolutely so rapid mq obviously
is the
amqp message brokers and it's probably
the primary message broker does redis
also support amqp or how do you actually
support redis as a back end so
unlike celery
uh where there are
a lot of design bugs and problems and
abstraction problems
combo's design is brilliant but it does
is that it emulates amqp 0.9.1
logically
in code so we create a virtual transport
with virtual channels and bindings
and since redis is programmable you can
use lua or you can just use a pipeline
then you can just implement whatever you
need within redis
vedics provides a lot of
uh fundamental constructs
for storing messages in order or in some
order which provides you a way to
implement it and emulate it now do i
understand the implementation partially
because
the reality of an open source project is
that some things are not well maintained
but it works and
there are many other us platforms
execution platforms which use redis as
the sole message broker such as rq
and they are a lot simpler than serving
awesome so obviously that means that i
misspoke when i said salary kind of
supports rapid mq and redis it's
basically standing on top of kombu and
kobu is the one that actually manages
this so
i think we have kind of like a
reasonable idea of what the various
parts of
is right so can we maybe take an example
right so to
say let's say i'm trying to set up a
simple online website for my i don't
know
a shop right so and i want to kind of
sell some basic clothing or somewheres
right
and i want to
also have this feature
where i want to send a delivery
order confirmation email or there are
various kind of notifications to my
customers
about the status of their orders right
so assume that i've kind of like built
this simple
website in flask and now
for these notification emails and
notifications maybe by sms right there
two or three different types of
notification
i want to use seller right so
for this right so for the simple thing
maybe i've set it up in a kubernetes
cluster somewhere on a cloud maybe
google or
amazon or something and i want to
implement salary
what would you recommend is the simplest
salary setup that can be used to support
this particular requirement
so if you're sending out emails you're
probably doing that by communicating
with an api
because there are providers that do it
for you and yeah yeah something like
twilio or maybe a mailchimp or something
like that yes yeah something like that
so what i'd recommend is to use
asynchronous io now salary provides
concurrency by pre-working
so you'd have multiple processes
but you can also use g event or eventlet
which make task execution asynchronous
by monkey patching the sockets
and
if this is your use case and you're
mostly i o bound what i suggest is
starting multiple salary processes
in one cluster which consumed from the
same message broker
and that way you'd have concurrency vote
on the cpu level and the i o level so
you'll be able to run you'll be able to
deliver
hundreds of thousands of emails per
second because
it's just calling an api and calling an
api as synchronously is very very
light on the system so there will be a
lot
of contact switching between green
threads
and you'd be able to utilize multiple
cpus by starting new processes so the
way i answer so then that means is that
i'll set up a maybe a new container or
something in which i will run the salary
worker and that will be reading from a
message broker but if you mention
kubernetes you can also auto scale based
on the queue size so let's say you have
one docker container with one process
that takes one cpu but it can only
process 200 tasks at a time now
you set that as a threshold for this
auto scaler and it will just start new
containers and process more more so if
you have 350 tasks all of them will be
concurrent now and then
we'll shut down that instance once we're
done right so as i understand it the
scaling will be on the salary workers
right and you will have say maybe one
instance of the rabbit mq or redis or
the message broker that kind of handles
the cues okay so how do i actually post
a message onto the queue do i have to
use a salary
client or can i use just post a message
somehow is there a particular standard
that i need to use
well the
salary has a protocol an application
protocol on top of ntp
which should pass over the messages body
you can't just publish
any message to salary
and expect it to work you need to use
salaries client there is a client for
node.js there is a client for php there
is a client for go a lot of things are
salary protocol compatible but most
people have been using celery for python
anyway right so from my flask website
container
i will use this i will install the
celery client module and then just post
the task to the message broker and then
the workers will pick it up so okay so
suppose let's take this example one step
further right so suppose i have kind of
gotten a little successful i'm kind of
tasting and my website is becoming
popular and i would like to get some
analytics on say how many
emails am i sending
or how many times that this particular
how many orders people are actually
making for a particular product so i
want to do some some sort of analysis
and i decided okay fine we will have a
separate analysis the data warehouse or
whatever and i cannot build the solution
but now i have the step this
asynchronous step where
in addition to creating the order in my
regular database i need to now
copy that data over or i need to
transform the data over and extract it
into my data warehouse right do you
think that is something
that should be done or that can be done
with salary or do you think that's
something that's not really suited for
salary in a better solution might be
kind of like a proper etl pipeline well
you can
in simple cases
it's very very easy even in course so
let's say you want to send a
confirmation email
and then write a record to the db that
says this email was sent so you update
some
the order with confirmation email sent
this is very very very typical but
performing intensive etls or queries
that takes hours to complete is simply
unnecessary what you're doing
essentially is hugging the capacity of
the cluster for something that won't
complete for a couple of hours and is
performed elsewhere so at the very least
you occupy one core routine
what most users do is occupy one process
because they use preform
okay so basically what you're saying is
that
it is possible to run that it's just
that you will kind of start using your
processes and kind of locking up some of
your
salary availability into this and so
basically that might be a problem okay
so
let's kind of get into a little bit of
okay so this is we've been talking about
the youth best case scenario so far
right
so what happens okay when say
for some certain reason my
i don't know i there was a sale on my
website and you know black friday or
something and the whole lot of orders
came in and my auto scaling kind of went
on i mean started putting up a lot of
salary workers and it reached the limits
that are sent set by my cloud provider
right so my cloud provider basically
started the kubernetes cluster started
killing and evicting the pods so what
actually happens
when a salary worker is killed
externally right so it is kind of
running out of memory of get skill and
what kind of recovery or retries are
possible in these kind of significant
scenarios right so when sarah is killed
generally speaking when seller is killed
it is entered a warm shutdown phase
where it gives a timeout for all tasks
to complete and then shuts down but sari
also has a cold shutdown which says kill
all tasks and exit immediately so it
really depends on the
signal you send if you send secret
you'll get a warm you get a call
shutdown and if you send the cdnt you'll
get a warm shutdown if you'll send
chicken twice you'll get a cold shot
down instead which makes sense because
usually you just click control c twice
you want to exit salary when it's
running in the program so when
kubernetes does this it also has a
timeout
on when it considers that container
to be shutted down gracefully so you
should be setting that to the timeout
that you've set for salaries one
shutdown or give it a fee even a little
buffer of a few more seconds just so you
won't get the alerts because these
containers were shuttered down
improperly and if you don't manage that
it will cause alert fatigue and you
won't know what's happening in your
cluster
right right so but what actually happens
to the task so if the if it is say a
long running task for example
does that mean that the task is can be
retried or is that what actually the
guarantees that salary provides yeah it
does mean it can be required but it
really depends on how you configure it
salary by default acknowledges tasks
early it's a reasonable choice
for early 2000s and 2010
but
nowadays
having it the other way around where you
acknowledge late
has some merits
so great acknowledgements are
very very useful for creating tasks
which can be requeued in case of failure
or if something happened because
you acknowledge the task only if it is
complete
you acknowledge early in case where the
task execution does not matter
you know you got the message and you
acknowledged it and then something went
wrong and you don't want it to be in the
queue again
so if it's not i'd important right that
would be kind of something that you want
to acknowledge early
yeah and the fact that celery shows the
defaults
that makes tasks
not idempotent allowed to be
non-independent is in my opinion a bad
decision because
if tasks are independent they can be
retried very very easily so i think
salary should encourage that by design
so if you have late acknowledgement you
acknowledge the task by the end of it if
it fails or if it succeeds
and
that allows you to uh just
get the message back in case it was not
acknowledged so rabbitmq and redis has a
visibility timeout of some sort
and we use different terms but they have
a visibility timeout where the task is
still considered where the message is
still considered delivered and not
acknowledged after that while it returns
the message to
you back and it says that you know you
can consume it
now rabbit mq
also has something interesting when you
just shut down a connection so when you
kill sarah you shut down the connection
and you shut down the channel the
connection was bound to
which
is the way for rabbit and q to multiplex
messages over one connection right so to
find out scenario
no not the fan out scenario in the nqp
you have a connection
and you have a channel
now
you can have one tcp connection
but a channel multiplexes that
connection for multiple queues
so
logically if you look at the channel
logically it's like a virtual private
network like
right right
okay
so you're kind of like tunneling through
the same tcp connection you're sharing
it between multiple cues okay
understood yeah so when we close the
channel rabbitmq remembers which tasks
were delivered to that channel and it
immediately pops it back so it will then
kind of make it appear so if you have
say for whatever reason if you have say
multiple workers on multiple machines
multiple docker containers say and one
of them is killed then what you're
saying is that rabbit and cube no said
okay that channel has died or closed and
it remembers the tasks that were on that
channel pulls that and puts it on the
other channel so that the other worker
can work on it
yeah this is called a knack where a
message is not acknowledged if it's
not acknowledged it's returned back to
the queue it originated from right
awesome so so you said that there is a
similar visibility
mechanism for redis as well correct yeah
not similar because redis does not
really have channels
and
we do not track which tasks we delivered
where which
because that could be disastrous for the
scalability of the system on top of
radius so what we do is
only provide a timeout a maximum timeout
this is also uh relevant in sqs as well
because both of them has the same
concept of visibility timeout where if
the task does not get processed after
let's say 360 seconds it's returned back
to the queue
so it's a basic timeout
time scale db from your friends at time
scale is the leading open source
relational database with support for
time series data
time series data is time stamped so you
can measure how a system is changing
time series data is relentless and
requires a database like time scale db
with speed and petabyte scale
time scale db is the postgres you know
and love with time series super powers
familiarity flexibility speed that's
time scale
visit them today at tsdb.co
se radio
that's tsdb.com
right so is that something that as a
developer so in in my earlier scenario
say suppose we were doing an etl as well
as the notification notifications
usually will happen quickly whereas an
etl can take say a couple of hours as
well so is that a case where we can go
to redis or we can configure in salary
that hey for this type of task
increase the visibility timeout so that
it doesn't
okay
no
unfortunately no actually that's a good
idea but what you can do is create two
salary processes salary
processors which have different
configurations and
i'd say actually
that these are two different projects
with two different code bases in my
opinion right so you basically
separate them into two workers one
worker that is just handling the
long-running tasks and the other workers
are doing the notification
okay cool
so obviously when there are failures and
when there are things like this you
obviously also want to have some kind of
visibility into what is happening inside
a salary worker right so can you talk a
little bit about how we can monitor
tasks and how maybe the logging in tasks
are done
currently the only monitoring tool we
have is flower which is another open
source project that listens to the
events protocol salary publishes to the
broker
and gets the metadata from there but
basically the
result backend is where you monitor how
tasks are going you can report that
state of the task you can provide custom
states you can provide progress
context whatever context you have to the
progress of the task and that could
allow you to monitor it with an external
system that just listens to changes
just like flower if for example you'd
have something that translates this to
statsd
you could have monitoring as well celery
is not very observable one of the
goals of salary next gen
would be to integrate it completely with
open
telemetry so it will just
provide a lot more data into what's
going on right now the only monitoring
we provide is through the event system
you can also inspect to check the
current status of a survey process
so you can see how many active tasks
there are
you can get that in json too so if you
do that periodically and push that to uh
your logging system maybe you can make
that of use
awesome okay so obviously if you don't
have that much visibility in monitoring
how does actually salary handle
logging so is it possible to kind of
extend the logging of salary so that we
can add more logging to maybe try and
see if we can get more data information
out of the
on what is happening from that
perspective well logging is configurable
as much as django's logging is
configurable
uh okay so it's like general extension
of the python logging libraries yeah
pretty much and one of the things that
survey does is is that it tries to be
compatible with django
so it can take the django configuration
and apply it to celery
for logging
and that's why they work the same way as
far as
logging more data that's entirely
possible the concern is very extensible
when it's user facing
so you could just override the task
class
and override the hooks before start
after start stuff like that you could
register to signals and log data from
the signals you could actually implement
open telemetry and i think
in the country package of open telemetry
there is an implementation for salary
not sure how well that's the state right
now so it is entirely possible to do
that
it's just that it wasn't implemented yet
so it's not kind of like native to
salary per se
but it is it provides extension points
and hooks so that you can implement it
yourself as you see fit okay cool so
moving on to a little bit more about you
know how to scale a seller
implementation earlier in you had
mentioned and you had said that a
salary is a good option for startups
but and then it grows but as you grow
and start you start seeing some of the
problems or the limitations of a salary
implementation right obviously when
you're in a startup mode and then you're
a developer there you want to kind of
maximize
the usage of whatever choice you made so
if you made salary choice then basically
you would want to first try to see
how far you can take it before then you
go with the other with another
alternative so what are the typical
bottlenecks
that
usually occur with salary right is a
what is the first thing that kind of
starts
failing or what are the first warning
signs that your salary set up is not
working as you thought it would be
well for starter very large workflows
celery has a concept of canvases
which are building blocks for
creating a workflow dynamically not
declaratively by but by just composing
tasks together
ad hoc and delaying them
now
when you have a very large
workflow a very large canvas that is
serialized back into a message broker
things get messy
because celery's protocol was not
designed for that scale so it could just
turn up to be
10 gigabytes or 20 gigabytes and it will
try to push that to the broker we've had
an issue about it and i just told the
user to use compression
supports compression of the of its
protocol and it's something i encourage
people to use
when they start growing from
the startup stage to the growing stage
and have requirements that are not up to
what siri was designed for so when you
say compression what exactly does that
mean does that mean that i can actually
take a salary message and zip it and
send it and they will
automatically pick it up yeah oh awesome
right right right okay cool so if your
message size becomes too large or if
you've got too many parameters in your
message like you said you're creating
canvas or it's a set of operations that
you're trying to do then you can kind of
zip it up and then send to that that's
interesting i did not know that that's
that's very interesting another thing is
trying to run machine learning pipelines
because machine learning pipelines uh
for the most part use prefork themselves
in python to paralyze work
and that doesn't work well with prefer
it sometimes does it sometimes doesn't
billiard is voodoo to me and
very much not documented billiard is
very
so just tell me what billiard is yes
billiard is series
implementation of multi-processing it's
a report that allows you to support
multiple python versions in the same
library
with some extensions to it that
i
really don't know how they work billiard
was the component that was never ever
documented
so the most important component of siri
right now is something we don't know
what to do with
right
interesting so billiard essentially
would be something that you want to you
want to use if you want to kind of if
you have some components that are for
different version python version or if
they are
not standard kind of implementations
yeah
job lib has a similar project called
loki which does a very very similar
thing
and i've actually thought about dumping
billiard and using their implementation
but
that would require a lot of work and
given that
python has now
a viable way
to remove the global interpreter lock
then maybe we don't need to invest that
much in prefork anymore
now for those who don't know python and
ruby and lua and node.js and other
interpreted languages
have a global interpreter log this is a
singular mutex
which controls the entire program so
when two threads try to run a python
byte code only one of them succeeds
because
a lot of operations in python are atomic
so if you have a list and reappend to it
you expect that to happen without an
additional lock
right how does that kind of affect
salary is that basically
one of the reasons why are we using an
event loop for reading from the message
key
yeah that's one of the reasons for using
an event loop for reading for the
message queue because we don't want to
use a lot of cpu power to pull and
block right and that's also probably why
we've python the in the cellar
implementation you favor process forking
versus threats in the
okay cool so apparently having one mutex
is better than having
infinite amount of mutaxes because for
every list you create you'll have to
create a lock to make to ensure
all operations that are guaranteed to be
atomic to be atomic and it's at least
one lock
so removing the gill is very very hard
and someone found an approach that
appears very very promising i'm very
much hoping that celery could by default
work with threads
because it will simplify the code base
greatly and we could leave our
preforking as an extension for someone
else to implement okay awesome
right so obviously we talked about these
kind of bottlenecks that we're seeing
over here and we obviously know that the
or the threading approach is simpler
other than salary obviously we've kind
of preferred to there are other
approaches to doing this particular task
right so the whole idea of message
queueing and task execution is is not
new we have other orchestration tools
right there are things called workflow
orchestration tools in fact i think some
of them in fact use salary as well can
you maybe talk a little bit about
what is the difference between a
workflow orchestration tool and a
library like salary
so salary is a lower level library it's
a building block of those tools
because as i said
it's a task execution platform you just
say
i want this task to be executed and at
some point it will and if it won't
you'll know about it so these tools can
use uh celery as a building block
for publishing their own tasks
and executing something that they need
to do
on top of that yeah
okay cool so
given that there is these options like
airflow and luigi which are a couple of
the floor floor orchestration tools
we talked about the canvas object right
where you can actually do multiple tasks
or kind of orchestrate multiple tasks do
you think that it might be better to
maybe use these higher level tools to do
that kind of orchestration or do you
feel that it's something that that can
be handled by salary as well i don't
think celery was meant for uh workflow
orchestration
it was meant the canvases were meant to
be something very very simple you want
each task to maintain the singular
responsibility principle
so what you do is just separate the
functionality we discussed
for sending a confirmation email and
updating the database to two tasks and
you launch a chain of the sending of the
email and then updating the database
that helps because each operation can be
retried separately so that's why
canvases exist they were not meant to
run your daily bi batch jobs
with 5 000 tasks in parallel that return
one response
right right
understood understood great so that's
obviously like we said i think we've
talked about
machine learning is
not something that is a good fit with
accelerating regarding apache airflow
did you know that it can run over celery
so it actually uses celery as a building
block as a potential window block now
task is another system
that is uh
related more to numpy
that can also run in surrey because
dublin
which is the job runner for dusk
can run tasks in salary to process them
in parallel so many many tools actually
use celery as a foundational building
block right so
das if i'm not mistaken is also
i think a
task parallelization would say it's a
way to kind of break up your process or
your machine learning thing into
multiple parallel processes that can run
in parallel so it's interesting that it
uses celery underneath it so it kind of
gives you kind of like this idea that
okay
as we kind of go up and become
more sophisticated in our workflows and
in our pipelines that there are these
larger constructs that you can probably
build on top of celery that kind of
handle that so one kind of different
thought that i was thinking about when
looking at celery was the idea of event
driven architectures right so there are
entire architectures nowadays that
basically are driven around this idea of
okay you put an event in a in a bus or
in a queue or you have some kind of
broker and everything is events and you
basically have everything is kind of
resolved as you go through all these
events so
maybe let's talk a little bit about is
that something that salary
can fit into or is that something that
is
more better handled by a specialized
tool say like maybe an enterprise
service bus or something like that
i don't think anyone thought it could
but it can
so
as i mentioned uh regarding the
topologies the message topologies that
npp provides us
we can use those
to implement an event-driven
architecture using celery you have
different workers with different
projects
using the same task name
so basically when you just delay the
task
when you send it what will happen will
depend on the routing key because if you
bind two queues to a topic exchange and
you provide a routing key for each one
you'd be able to
route it to the right direction and have
something that responds to an event in a
certain way just because of the routing
key you could also fan out which is
again you a user posted something
and then well everybody needs to know
about it so in essence
this task is actually an event but it's
still treated as a job instead of as an
event this is something i intend to
change in enterprise integration
patterns there are three types of
messages the enterprise integration
patterns is a
very very good book
about messaging in general it's a little
bit outdated but not by very much
it's still relevant today
and it defines three types of messages
you have a command
you have an event
and you have a document a command is a
task this is what we're doing today an
event is what it describes what happened
now salary in response to that should
execute
multiple tasks so when survey gets an
event it should publish multiple tasks
to the message broker that's what it
should do and document message is just
data this is very very common with kafka
for example you just push the log
the exact log line that you received and
someone else will do something with it
who knows what
maybe they'll push it to the elastic
search maybe they'll transform it maybe
not run analytics on it you don't care
you just push the data and that's also
something survey is missing because with
these three concepts
you can define workflows that
do a lot more than what salary can do so
if you have a document message you
essentially have a result of a task that
is modeled in messaging terms so you can
send the result to another queue
and there would be a transformer that
transforms it to a task that is the next
in line
for execution within the workflow
right okay so you could basically create
hierarchies of salary
workers that kind of handle different
types of things right so you have one
event that comes in and that kind of
triggers one salary worker which then in
turn broadcast more events or more tasks
and then that that is kind of picked up
by others okay very interesting so that
seems to be a pretty
interesting kind of thing towards kind
of implementing event-driven
architectures to be honest it sounds
like it's something that we can do very
simply without actually having to
buy or invest in a huge message queuing
or an enterprise service bus or
something like that and it sounds kind
of a great way to kind of check out or
try to experiment with event driven
architectures so just to kind of look
back a little bit to our earlier in the
beginning when we talked about the
difference between actors and salary
workers right and we mentioned that hey
an actor basically is a single
responsibility principle it does a
single thing and it sends one message
another
interesting thing about actors is the
fact is that they have supervisors and
they have this whole entire hierarchy
where you know when something when an
actor dies so when something happens it
kind of has a way to automatically
restart
are there any kind of
thoughts or design ideas around
doing something like that for salary is
there kind of like a way to say okay i'm
monitoring my salary workers this worker
when goes down or this particular task
is not running appropriately can i
restart it or can i create a new work or
is that something that we kind of right
now i know you mentioned that you can
have kubernetes do that by the during
the worker shutdown but then that
assumes that the work is shutting down
right if it's not shutting down or it's
just stuck or something like that then
how do we kind of handle that if the
process is stuck yeah if the process is
maybe it's running for too long or if
it's running out of memory or something
like that maybe we want to preemptively
you can limit to the amount of memory
each task takes and if it exceeds it
the worker goes down you can say how
many tasks you want to execute before a
worker process goes down and you can
retry tasks that is if a task fails and
you've configured we tried
you you've configured automatically
tries or just explicitly called retry
you can retry a task right entirely
powerful okay within the task itself you
can kind of specify that okay this task
needs to be retried if it fails
yeah you can retry for certain
exceptions or
explicitly call retry
by uh
binding the function but just say bind
equals true and you get the self of the
task instance
and then you can call the tasks classes
methods of that task
so you can call just uh you can get just
call retry there's also another thing
about that that i didn't mention
replacing in
4.4 i think
someone added a feature that allows you
to replace a canvas mid-flight so let's
say you
decided not to save the confirmation in
the database
but instead
since everything failed
and you haven't sent a single
confirmation email
just yet then you replace the task with
another task that
calls your alerting solution for example
or you could branch out essentially so
this gives you a condition if this
happens
run for the rest of the canvas run this
run this
workflow or task for the else run this
workflow for the end of the task
right so we were talking about actors
celery had an attempt to write an actor
framework on top of the existing
framework it's called cell
now
it was just an attempt no one developed
it very far
but i think it's the wrong approach
celery was designed
with an add-on framework
that
had patches over patches over the years
and it's
almost acto-like but it's not so what i
thought was that we could just create an
active framework
in python
that will be de facto a go-to
actual framework in python for backend
packages
and that framework would be easy enough
to use
for occasional contributors
to be able to contribute to salary
because right now the case is that in
order to contribute to salary
you need to know
a lot about the code and how it
interacts
so what we want is to replace the
internals but keep the same public api
so if we bump a major version
everything still works
right
right awesome
that sounds like a great approach
yeah that is a great approach it's
called uh project jumpstarter the
repository can be found in series
organization
and you're more than welcome to
contribute would you like me to speak a
little bit more about the idea or not
absolutely so i was just going to ask so
is there a roadmap for jumpstarter or is
this something that is still kind of in
the early
thinking of prototyping phase uh it's
still in the early prototyping but there
is a direction
where we're going
the
focus is on observability and ergonomics
so you need to be able to know how to
write a dsl for example in python let me
give you the basic concepts of
jumpstarter jumpstarter is a special
active framework because each actor
is modeled by an hierarchical state
machine in a state machine you have
transitions
from a
to b
and from
b to c and c to e et cetera et cetera et
cetera or from a to z skipping all the
rest but you can't have
conditions for
which state can transition to which
another state in a hierarchical state
machine you can have state a
which can only transition to b and c
because there are child states of state
a
and you can have state d which cannot
transition to b and c
because they're not children states
right okay so it's kind of like a
directional
almost like a directed acyclic graph not
child states of d
that was it not
yeah yeah uh no no so it's almost like a
directed acyclic graph right so it's
essentially yeah exactly yeah yeah okay
cool so that is a direct a cyclic graph
that you can attach hooks on so you can
attach a hook before the transition
happens after the transition happens
when you exit the state when you enter
the state
when an error occurs
so you can model
the entire life cycle of the worker is
in the state machine
now
the basic definition of an actor
has a state machine with a life cycle in
it
just uh
batteries included you come with
batteries included you have the state
machine already configured
to uh starting and stopping itself so
you have a star trigger and stop trigger
you can also change the state of the
actor to healthy or unhealthy or
degraded
you could restart it and everything that
happens happens through the state
machine now on top of that
we add two important concepts
the concepts of actor tasks
and resources actor tasks are tasks that
extend the actors state machine you can
only run one task at a time so
what that provides you is essentially a
workflow where you can say i'm calling
for data and once i am done pulling for
data i'm going to transition to
processing data and then it goes back
again to polling data because you can
define loops in the state machine it's
true and complete it's not actually a
tag
it's a graph where you can make loops
and cycles
and essentially model any
any programming logic you want so
basically the actor does not violate the
basic three axioms of actors which is
having a single responsibility having
the ability to spawn other actors and
message passing
but it also has this new feature
where you
can manage
the execution of the actor by defining
states so let's say
when you are in degraded state your
integrated state because the actor's
health check to that checks uh s3
fails so you can't do anything
but you can still process the tasks that
you have
so this allow running
the pole tasks from the degraded state
but you can transition from degraded to
processing data so that models
everything you need now in addition to
that i've managed to create an api that
manages resources
which are context managers in a
declarative way so you just define a
function you return a context manager or
an async context manager
and decorate it with a resource
and it will be available to the actor as
an attribute
and it will be automatically cleaned
when the actor goes down
uh okay
but one question i have was that so you
mentioned that this particular model
will be built or jumpstarted without
actually changing the major api
of salary right so how does this kind of
map into a task so does it mean that
okay the
basically all the
classes that we have
will remain unchanged and they kind of
like map into actors now instead of just
functioning
so salary has a task registry which
registers all the tasks in the app right
so this is very easy to model you have
an actor
which
defines one unit of concurrency
and
has
all the tasks salary is registered to in
the actor and therefore when that actor
gets a message
it can process that task and
it's busy you know it's busy because
it's in the state the
task ah okay
right
so it's almost like you're building a
signaling
of the
the whole framework itself the context
in which the tasks run is now basically
inside the actor and so now the active
model on top then allows you to kind of
understand
the state of that particular
processing unit right okay that's great
that's awesome so is there anything else
that we have not covered today that
you'd like to talk about in terms of the
topic
yeah it's been very very hard to work on
this project during the pandemic and if
i were to do it without the support of
my clients
i'd have much less time to actually
give the attention this project needs
this project needs to be revamped and we
very much like you to be involved
and if you can be involved and use
salary
please donate right now we only have a
budget of five thousand dollars a year
or five thousand five hundred dollars
something like that
and we would very much like to reach a
budget that allows us to
put more resources in so if you have
problems with salary or if you have
something that
you want to fix in salary or a feature
to add you can just contact us we'd be
very much happy to help you with it
awesome so in terms of that so that's a
great point how can our listeners
get in touch about the salary project is
that something that is there in the main
website
regarding this donation aspect of it or
the sponsoring aspect of it yes it is
and we can just go to our open
collective or to a github repository we
have set up the funding from there
right so awesome in that case
when we post this on to the software
engineering radio website i'll make sure
that these links are there and that you
know our listeners can access them so
thank you very much omer this was a very
enjoyable session i really
enjoyed speaking with you about this
have a great day you too
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening